<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ira Parsons</title>
    <link>https://iraparsons.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ira Parsons</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://iraparsons.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/blogs/2022-05-01-/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/blogs/2022-05-01-/</guid>
      <description>  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Ira is a graduate research assistant in the department of Wildlife, Fisheries, and Aquaculture as well as the Animal Dairy Sciences at Mississippi State University. Growing up on the family farm in Northeast Kansas, Ira developed a love and passion for animals, the outdoors and nature. He received his bachelors from Kansas State University in 2015, where he majored in Feed Science and Management. Driven by a desire to learn and pursue a career with animals, he joined the class of ’17 at Texas A&amp;amp;M in College Station, where he received his Master of Science in Animal Science.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>Ira L. Parsons
Quantitative Ecology and Spatial Technologies Laboratory
Department of Wildlife, Fisheries, and Aquaculture
Mississippi State University
775 Stone Blvd
Mississippi State University, MS 39762
ilp28@msstate.edu</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CV</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/cv/</guid>
      <description>Ira Lloyd Parsons Mississippi State University, Thomson Hall · Mississippi State, MS 39762 · 913-565-0896 · ilp28@msstate.edu
Education
Doctor of Philosophy in Forest Resources, Mississippi State University December 2022
concentration: Wildlife, Fisheries and Aquaculture, GPA 4.00
Mississippi State University, Mississippi State, Mississippi, 39762
Dissertation Title: Animal Husbandry in the 21 st Century: Understanding beef cattle grazing systems ecology using precision technology_
Chapters: Thesis Objective: Demonstrate prospective uses of tracking collars and accelerometers to study fine-scale movement and behaviors related to animal cattle growth/production, energy expenditure, and pasture space use given landscape resource distribution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/publications/</guid>
      <description>Published
Kayser, William W. C., G.E. Carstens, I.L. Parsons , K.E. Washburn, S.D. Lawdon, W.E. Pinchak, E. Chevaux, and A.L. 2020. Skidmore. Efficacy of statistical process control procedures to identify deviations in continuously measured physiologic and behavioral variables in beef steers experimentally challenged with Mannheimia haemolytica. Journal of Animal Science. 2020 98:1-11
 Parsons, I.L. , J.R. Johnson, W.C. Kayser, and G.E. Carstens. 2019. Characterization of feeding behavior traits in steers with divergent residual feed intake consuming a high-grain diet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
