<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ira Parsons</title>
    <link>https://iraparsons.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ira Parsons</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://iraparsons.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Silver Carp - helping hands &amp; new experiences</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/blogs/2022-08-08-silver-carp-project-helping-hands-and-new-experiences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/blogs/2022-08-08-silver-carp-project-helping-hands-and-new-experiences/</guid>
      <description>Lending a helping hand to fellow grad students is perhaps the most rewarding and enjoyable educational activities which graduate students can partake in. Benefits are two-fold. First, you gain the satisfactory feeling that comes from helping out a fellow student and friend while secondly, learning something more about a part of science and nature which heretofore you knew absolutely nothing about. And all at zero cost, no stress, and potentially some good food and comradeship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Ira is a graduate research assistant in the department of Wildlife, Fisheries, and Aquaculture at Mississippi State University. Growing up on the family farm in Northeast Kansas, Ira developed a love for animals, the outdoors, and nature. He received his bachelors in Feed Science and Management from Kansas State University in 2015 before moving to Texas A&amp;amp;M where he completed a Masters of Science in Animal Science with a concentration in Ruminant Nutrition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Automated walk-over-weigh system, methods to track daily body mass and growth in grazing steers</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/current-research/wow/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/current-research/wow/</guid>
      <description>Body weight is a critical component for monitoring animal body mass, body condition, nutritional status, and health. However, traditional methods of collecting body weight are stressful, costly, and logistically impractical with cattle on extensive landscapes. Remote systems capable of collecting individual animal body weight provide a potential solution, but automatic systems may collect spurious measurements. The objectives of this study were to 1) describe the utility of using a remote weight capture system, 2) develop methods for identifying and removing spurious measurements, and 3) cross-validate automatically collected weights with static chute collected weights.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>Ira L. Parsons
Quantitative Ecology and Spatial Technologies Laboratory
Department of Wildlife, Fisheries, and Aquaculture
Mississippi State University
775 Stone Blvd
Mississippi State University, MS 39762
ilp28@msstate.edu</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Examining the relationship between sampling strategy, sample density, and interpolation strategy on mapping accuracy</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/current-research/landscape-sampling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/current-research/landscape-sampling/</guid>
      <description>Examining the relationship between sampling strategy, density, and map interpolation accuracy
Obtaining accurate and precise maps of landscape features often requires intensive spatial sampling and interpolation. The data required to generate reliable interpolated maps varies with sampling density and landscape heterogeneity. However, there has been no rigorous examination of sampling density relative to landscape characteristics and interpolation methods. Our objective was to characterize the 3-way relationship among sampling density, interpolation method, and landscape heterogeneity on interpolation accuracy and precision in simulated and in situ landscapes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/publications/</guid>
      <description>Published
Parsons, I.L. , Melanie M.R. Boudreau, Brandi B.B. Karisch, Amanda A.E. Stone, Durham D. Norman, Stephen S.L. Webb, Kristine K.O. Evans, and Garrett G.M. Street. Aiming for the optimum: examining complex relationships between sampling regime, sampling density, and landscape heterogeneity to accurately model resource availability. Submitted to Journal of Landscape Ecology. 2021. DOI: https://doi.org/10.21203/rs.3.rs-1005366/v1 In review.
 Kayser, William W. C., G.E. Carstens, I.L. Parsons , K.E. Washburn, S.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
