<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ira Parsons</title>
    <link>https://iraparsons.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ira Parsons</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://iraparsons.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Silver Carp - helping hands &amp; new experiences</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/blogs/2022-08-08-silver-carp-project-helping-hands-and-new-experiences/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/blogs/2022-08-08-silver-carp-project-helping-hands-and-new-experiences/</guid>
      <description>Lending a helping hand to fellow grad students is perhaps the most rewarding and enjoyable educational activities which graduate students can partake in. Benefits are two-fold. First, you gain the satisfactory feeling that comes from helping out a fellow student and friend while secondly, learning something more about a part of science and nature which heretofore you knew absolutely nothing about. And all at zero cost, no stress, and potentially some good food and comradeship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/about/</guid>
      <description>Ira is a graduate research assistant in the department of Wildlife, Fisheries, and Aquaculture at Mississippi State University. Growing up on the family farm in Northeast Kansas, Ira developed a love for animals, the outdoors, and nature. He received his bachelors in Feed Science and Management from Kansas State University in 2015 before moving to Texas A&amp;amp;M where he did a Masters of Science in Animal Science. With a focus on improving management of natural resources, Ira is pursuing his passion, exploring the nexus between plant and animal ecology to maximize efficiency and sustainability for livestock production.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/contact/</guid>
      <description>Ira L. Parsons
Quantitative Ecology and Spatial Technologies Laboratory
Department of Wildlife, Fisheries, and Aquaculture
Mississippi State University
775 Stone Blvd
Mississippi State University, MS 39762
ilp28@msstate.edu</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://iraparsons.com/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://iraparsons.com/publications/</guid>
      <description>Published
Kayser, William W. C., G.E. Carstens, I.L. Parsons , K.E. Washburn, S.D. Lawdon, W.E. Pinchak, E. Chevaux, and A.L. 2020. Skidmore. Efficacy of statistical process control procedures to identify deviations in continuously measured physiologic and behavioral variables in beef steers experimentally challenged with Mannheimia haemolytica. Journal of Animal Science. 2020 98:1-11
 Parsons, I.L. , J.R. Johnson, W.C. Kayser, and G.E. Carstens. 2019. Characterization of feeding behavior traits in steers with divergent residual feed intake consuming a high-grain diet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
