<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-10-23T17:42:23-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ira Parsons</title><subtitle>A grazing ecologists using precision livestock technology, metabolic theory, and data science to improve efficiency in extensive landscapes</subtitle><author><name>Ira Parsons</name></author><entry><title type="html">About the Author</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/about-the-author" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About the Author" /><published>2023-10-23T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-10-23T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/about-the-author</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/about-the-author"><![CDATA[<p>Ira Parsons is a post-doctoral research associate with the Animal Science Department at South Dakota State University. Growing up on the family ranch in Northeast Kansas, Ira was active in 4-H and FFA, where he developed love for animals and passion for learning through livestock projects and judging team competitions. He earned a bachelors in Feed Science and Management from Kansas State University before pursuing a Masters in Animal Science from Texas A&amp;M University, with a concentration in Ruminant Nutrition. His doctorate work focused on utilizing advanced biometric, remote sensing, and modeling methods to study livestock grazing systems, earning a PhD in Forest Resources with a Concentration in Wildlife, Fisheries and Aquaculture. Currently, Ira works with a diverse team with broad interest in rangeland ecology, animal science, and systems dynamics with a specific focus to employing precision livestock technology to monitor and improve beef cattle production efficiency through research and extension programs in the Northern Great Plains.</p>

<p>Ira Parsons is a post-doctoral research associate with the Animal Science Department at South Dakota State University. Growing up on the family ranch in Northeast Kansas, Ira was active in 4-H and FFA, where he developed love for animals and passion for learning through livestock projects and judging team competitions. He earned a bachelors in Feed Science and Management from Kansas State University before pursuing a Masters in Ruminant Nutrition from Texas A&amp;M University. His PhD work at Mississippi State University focused on remote sensing and modeling methods to study livestock grazing systems. Currently, Ira works with a diverse team at SDSU with broad interest in rangeland ecology and livestock systems with a specific focus on using precision livestock technology to monitor and improve beef cattle production efficiency in the Northern Great Plains.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ira Parsons</name></author><category term="about" /><category term="people" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ira Parsons is a post-doctoral research associate with the Animal Science Department at South Dakota State University. Growing up on the family ranch in Northeast Kansas, Ira was active in 4-H and FFA, where he developed love for animals and passion for learning through livestock projects and judging team competitions. He earned a bachelors in Feed Science and Management from Kansas State University before pursuing a Masters in Animal Science from Texas A&amp;M University, with a concentration in Ruminant Nutrition. His doctorate work focused on utilizing advanced biometric, remote sensing, and modeling methods to study livestock grazing systems, earning a PhD in Forest Resources with a Concentration in Wildlife, Fisheries and Aquaculture. Currently, Ira works with a diverse team with broad interest in rangeland ecology, animal science, and systems dynamics with a specific focus to employing precision livestock technology to monitor and improve beef cattle production efficiency through research and extension programs in the Northern Great Plains.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/Ira_profile.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/Ira_profile.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wow</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/WOW" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wow" /><published>2023-07-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-07-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/WOW</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/WOW"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Ira Parsons</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Examining the relationship between sampling strategy, sample density, and interpolation strategy on mapping accuracy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Landscape-sampling" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Examining the relationship between sampling strategy, sample density, and interpolation strategy on mapping accuracy" /><published>2022-09-01T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-09-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Landscape-sampling</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Landscape-sampling"><![CDATA[<p>Obtaining accurate and precise maps of landscape features often requires intensive spatial sampling and interpolation. 
The data required to generate reliable interpolated maps varies with sampling density and landscape heterogeneity. 
However, there has been no rigorous examination of sampling density relative to landscape characteristics and interpolation methods. Our objective was to characterize the 3-way relationship among sampling density, interpolation method, and landscape heterogeneity on interpolation accuracy and precision in simulated and in situ landscapes. We simulated landscapes of variable heterogeneity and sampled at increasing densities using gridded and random strategies. We applied three local interpolation methods (i.e., Inverse Distance Weighting, Universal Kriging, and Nearest Neighbor) to the sampled data and estimated accuracy (slope and intercept) and precision (R2) between interpolated surfaces and the original surface. Finally, we applied these analyses to in situ data using a normalized difference vegetation index raster collected from pasture with various resolutions. In our simulations, all interpolation methods and sampling strategies yielded similar accuracy and precision except in the case of Universal Kriging with random sampling. Additionally, low heterogeneity and increasing sample density improved both accuracy and precision, with cross-validation slopes and R2 values approaching optimal values. In situ analysis demonstrated that heterogeneity decreased with resolution. Nearest Neighbor under both sampling strategies and Universal Kriging using the gridded sampling strategy had the highest accuracy and precision. Decreased heterogeneity and increased sampling density improved accuracy and precision for all combinations of interpolation method and sampling strategies. Heterogeneity of the  landscape is a major influence on the accuracy and precision of interpolated maps. There is a need to create structured tools to aid in determining sampling design most appropriate for interpolation methods across landscapes of various heterogeneity.</p>

<p><img src="/Users/ira/Documents/GitHub/irap93.github.io/images/samplingloc.png" alt="Sampling locations" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Ira Parsons</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="research" /><category term="sampling" /><category term="landscapes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Obtaining accurate and precise maps of landscape features often requires intensive spatial sampling and interpolation. The data required to generate reliable interpolated maps varies with sampling density and landscape heterogeneity. However, there has been no rigorous examination of sampling density relative to landscape characteristics and interpolation methods. Our objective was to characterize the 3-way relationship among sampling density, interpolation method, and landscape heterogeneity on interpolation accuracy and precision in simulated and in situ landscapes. We simulated landscapes of variable heterogeneity and sampled at increasing densities using gridded and random strategies. We applied three local interpolation methods (i.e., Inverse Distance Weighting, Universal Kriging, and Nearest Neighbor) to the sampled data and estimated accuracy (slope and intercept) and precision (R2) between interpolated surfaces and the original surface. Finally, we applied these analyses to in situ data using a normalized difference vegetation index raster collected from pasture with various resolutions. In our simulations, all interpolation methods and sampling strategies yielded similar accuracy and precision except in the case of Universal Kriging with random sampling. Additionally, low heterogeneity and increasing sample density improved both accuracy and precision, with cross-validation slopes and R2 values approaching optimal values. In situ analysis demonstrated that heterogeneity decreased with resolution. Nearest Neighbor under both sampling strategies and Universal Kriging using the gridded sampling strategy had the highest accuracy and precision. Decreased heterogeneity and increased sampling density improved accuracy and precision for all combinations of interpolation method and sampling strategies. Heterogeneity of the landscape is a major influence on the accuracy and precision of interpolated maps. There is a need to create structured tools to aid in determining sampling design most appropriate for interpolation methods across landscapes of various heterogeneity.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/samplingloc.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/samplingloc.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Silver carp: Helping hands and new experiences</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/silver-carp-helping-hands-and-new-experiences" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Silver carp: Helping hands and new experiences" /><published>2022-08-08T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2022-08-08T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/silver-carp-helping-hands-and-new-experiences</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/silver-carp-helping-hands-and-new-experiences"><![CDATA[<p>Lending a helping hand to fellow grad students is perhaps the most rewarding and enjoyable educational activities which graduate students can partake in. Benefits are two-fold. First, you gain the satisfactory feeling that comes from helping out a fellow student and friend while also learning something more about a part of science and nature which heretofore you knew absolutely nothing about. And all at zero cost, no stress, good comradeship and potentially free food. This past weekend, I had the opportunity helping a fellow student track Silver Carp (<em>Hypophthalmichthys molitrix</em>) within the lower reaches of the Yazzoo river system. As a Kansan unfamiliar with the ways of boats, big murky water, and muddy rivers, it was certainly an experience. And even though these invasive fish are known to exist throughout the Mississippi River drainage system, an area which includes the lower reaches of the Kansas river, I had personally never experienced the fish before, a fact which only served to intensify my intrigue.</p>

<p>The river experience began like something straight out of a National Geographic nature documentary. Numerous times I wished I had a way of safely bringing along my camera and lens to photograph the white egrets (<em>Ardea alba</em>) who were frequently observed stalking the banks, or the quick moving birds of various types who often stood in stark contrast along the banks where the glass smooth water met the vibrant green contrast of the grassy banks. Our primary purpose that day was to download data and active track fish previously tagged with acoustic transponders to identify their geo-location, which could then be used to map their use of the sprawling water system. The active tracker utilizes an underwater microphone system designed to detect the low frequency noises emitted by the active acoustic transponders inserted into the body cavity of tagged fish, and necessitates traveling no more than 5 - 7 miles an hour. This provided the perfect opportunity to observe nature and fish in all of their glory.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/20220807_094818.jpg" alt="Silver carp jump as an unusual evasive manuver to avoid predaters, often with no seeming direction or plan once the jump is initiated.They often body slam back into the water, splashing murky water over everyone unfortuneate enough to be nearby. A vibration or wake, common when fishing boats are idling or coming of plane, causes them to jump in their random and frustrationg fashion. This propensity to jump, sometimes 10 feet or more in the air, makes a hazard for people in passing boats, where a several kilogram fish can pack quite a wallop. One smacking you in the face can feel like getting punched in the nose." /></p>

<p>Unfortunately, our trolling speed seemed to produce exactly the freak out frequency for all Silver Carp, who rewarded us for our efforts by giving us an hours long demonstration along the miles and miles of muddy water we transversed over the course of our two day adventure. An astute observer quickly realizes that unlike other life forms which God chose to grace our planet, fish, and Silver Carp in particular, are definitively not among the more intelligent. Rather than jumping in a logical direction away from the source of perceived danger, they randomly launch themselves, wiggling and thrashing in no particular direction and seemingly not plan to deal with gravity, as they haphazardly splash back to the water. No matter their age, they took on the appearance of uncoordinated adolescents or gangly puppies, repeatedly surprised by gravity when it halted their upward leap. A great deal of them slammed themselves into the hard aluminium bottom of our boat, causing a tremendous ruckus and mad scramble to get them out before their flopping made them bleed all over our equipment. To reward our efforts, the stranded fish twisted and contorted themselves in a massive mess of blood and feces. By the end of the day, I am pretty sure that all of us were dog tired. I’m not sure if the fish were or not, but I know I was, and I am certain my fellow grad student was as well.</p>

<p><img src="assets/img/20220807_142436.jpg" alt="Dirty jeans" /></p>

<p>Overall, despite the mud, slime, fish smell, hot sun, and tiring trip, I think that the trip was a success on multiple fronts. First, I learned something about myself. I don’t like fish. But more importantly, I learned something about the river ecosystem by observing it with a fellow student for whom studying it was their current passtion. Further, I gained a deeper appreciation for the beauty of our rivers and the danger posed by invasive species. I learned something more about a field I personally specialize in, movement ecology, the interaction between organisms and their environment, and the technology available to allow scientists an inquisitive peak into that dimension. And perhaps most important, I got to help out a graduate student in their quest to finish their degree, while furthering the scientific pursuit of knowledge. And perhaps most importantly, I learned that as much as I hate going fishing and not catching anything, having the fish jump directly into my boat is definitely not all it was dreamed to be.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ira Parsons</name></author><category term="research" /><category term="research" /><category term="fish" /><category term="animal movement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Lending a helping hand to fellow grad students is perhaps the most rewarding and enjoyable educational activities which graduate students can partake in. Benefits are two-fold. First, you gain the satisfactory feeling that comes from helping out a fellow student and friend while also learning something more about a part of science and nature which heretofore you knew absolutely nothing about. And all at zero cost, no stress, good comradeship and potentially free food. This past weekend, I had the opportunity helping a fellow student track Silver Carp (Hypophthalmichthys molitrix) within the lower reaches of the Yazzoo river system. As a Kansan unfamiliar with the ways of boats, big murky water, and muddy rivers, it was certainly an experience. And even though these invasive fish are known to exist throughout the Mississippi River drainage system, an area which includes the lower reaches of the Kansas river, I had personally never experienced the fish before, a fact which only served to intensify my intrigue.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/20220807_070415.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/20220807_070415.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>